Guide to the James T. Babb Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
James T. Babb Correspondence
1962-1968
1965-1968
GEN MSS 1011
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
4.18
(12 boxes)
Incoming correspondence and outgoing typescript carbons, most 1965-1968, with some related writings and speeches by Babb, typescript carbon. Some correspondence concerns Yale University Library, Library acquisitions, donors Paul Mellon and the Beinecke family, and the founding of the Yale Center for British Art. Other correspondence relates to Babb's collecting of William Beckford and William McFee, or to his work in assembling a library for the White House, 1962-1967, including correspondence with Jacqueline Kennedy, Arthur M. Schlesinger, and other White House staff of Presidents John F. Kennedy and Lyndon Johnson. A few outgoing carbons, dictated during a trip to London, England, in 1964, are accompanied by dictation machine audio disks.
Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Bequest of James T. Babb (Yale 1924), 1968. Gift of James T. Babb (Yale 1924), 1967, as indicated in folder notes.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research. Previously restricted unless by permission of Beinecke Director or Yale University Librarian; restriction lifted during baseline processing, 2013.
Box 12 (dictation machine audio disks): Restricted fragile material. Reference copies may be requested. Consult Access Services for further information.
Scope and Contents
Incoming correspondence and outgoing typescript carbons, most 1965-1968, with some related writings and speeches by Babb, typescript carbon. Some correspondence concerns Yale University Library, Library acquisitions, donors Paul Mellon and the Beinecke family, and the founding of the Yale Center for British Art. Other correspondence relates to Babb's collecting of William Beckford and William McFee, or to his work in assembling a library for the White House, 1962-1967, including correspondence with Jacqueline Kennedy, Arthur M. Schlesinger, and other White House staff of Presidents John F. Kennedy and Lyndon Johnson. A few outgoing carbons, dictated during a trip to London, England, in 1964, are accompanied by dictation machine audio disks.
James T. Babb (1899-1968)
James T. Babb (Yale 1924), book and manuscript collector; Yale University Librarian, 1943-1965.
Arrangement
Organized into five series: I. White House Library, 1962-1967. II. Paul Mellon, 1967-1968. III. Chronological File, 1965-1968. IV. Alphabetical File, 1965-1968. V. Other Correspondence, 1964-1968.
Academic libraries -- Administration; Book collecting -- United States; Book collectors -- United States; Librarians -- United States -- Archives; Manuscripts -- Collectors and collecting -- United States; Rare book libraries -- United States; Audiovisual materials -- United States -- 20th Century; Sound recordings -- United States -- 20th Century; Librarians -- United States -- 20th Century; Book collectors -- United States -- 20th Century; Babb, James T. (James Tinkham), 1899-1968; Beckford, William, 1760-1844; Beinecke, Edwin J. (Edwin John), 1886-1970; Beinecke, Frederick W.; Beinecke, William Sperry; McFee, William, 1881-1966; Mellon, Paul; Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1929-1994; Schlesinger, Arthur M., Jr. (Arthur Meier), 1917-2007; Library of Congress; Yale Center for British Art; Yale University. Library; United States. President (1961-1963: Kennedy); United States. President (1963-1969: Johnson)
- White House Library, 1962-1967; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Library of Congress, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Onassis, Jacqueline Kennedy, 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Schlesinger, Arthur M. (Arthur Meier), 1962-1964 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Form letter for books wanted, undated (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - List of requests and correspondence, 1966 August 22 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - The White House library: a short-title list. Preface, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Other correspondence, 1966-1968; 6 (Box 1, Folder 7-12)
- Paul Mellon, 1967-1968; 0.21; (1 box)
  - Correspondence, 1967-1968; 3 (Box 2, Folder 13-15)
  - "The Paul Mellon Gallery of British Art and Center for British Studies." Report, 1967 December 11 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Chronological File, 1965-1968; 0.42; (1 box)
  - Outgoing carbons, 1965; 3 (Box 3, Folder 17-19)
  - Outgoing carbons, 1966 August 22 (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Outgoing carbons, 1966; 4 (Box 3, Folder 21-24)
  - Outgoing carbons, 1967; 4 (Box 3, Folder 25-28)
  - Outgoing carbons, 1968; 2 (Box 3, Folder 29-30)
- Alphabetical File, circa 1965-1968; 2.71; (7 boxes)
  - A-Al (Box 4, Folder 31)
  - Am-Az (Box 4, Folder 32)
  - Anglers' Club of New York (Box 4, Folder 33)
  - B-Bd (Box 4, Folder 34)
  - Be-Bh (Box 4, Folder 35)
  - Bi-Bk (Box 4, Folder 36)
  - Bl-Bq (Box 4, Folder 37)
  - Br-Bz (Box 4, Folder 38)
  - Babb, James T. Fund (Box 4, Folder 39)
  - Babb, James T. List, 1968 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  - Babb, James T. Spedan Lewis (Box 4, Folder 41)
  - Babb, James T. Speech, 1966 April 13 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  - Beckford collection (Box 4, Folder 43)
  - Beinecke, Edwin J. (Edwin John), 2 (Box 4, Folder 44-44a)
  - Beinecke, Frederick W. (Box 4, Folder 45)
  - Beinecke, William Sperry (Box 4, Folder 46)
  - Blair, Edwin F. (Box 4, Folder 47)
  - Books and manuscripts, recent offers (Box 4, Folder 48)
  - C-Cg (Box 5, Folder 49)
  - Cha (Box 5, Folder 50)
  - Chi-Cle (Box 5, Folder 51)
  - Cle-Clez (Box 5, Folder 52)
  - Co-Con (Box 5, Folder 53)
  - Coo-Coq (Box 5, Folder 54)
  - Cr-Cz (Box 5, Folder 55)
  - D (Box 5, Folder 56)
  - E-Ek (Box 5, Folder 57)
  - El-Ez (Box 5, Folder 58)
  - Eberstadt, Lindley (Box 5, Folder 59)
  - Elizabethan Club (Yale University), 2 (Box 5, Folder 60-60a)
  - F-Fk (Box 6, Folder 61)
  - Fl-Fz (Box 6, Folder 62)
  - First National Bank and Trust Company of New Haven (Box 6, Folder 63)
  - Fishing (Box 6, Folder 64)
  - Forest History Society (Box 6, Folder 65)
  - G-Gj (Box 6, Folder 66)
  - Gk-Gz (Box 6, Folder 67)
  - Grolier Club (Box 6, Folder 68)
  - H-Hn (Box 6, Folder 69)
  - Ho-Hz (Box 6, Folder 70)
  - I (Box 6, Folder 71)
  - J-Jl (Box 6, Folder 72)
  - Jm-Jz (Box 6, Folder 73)
  - Josephy, Alvin M., 1965 November 26 (Box 6, Folder 74)
    Immediate Source of Acquisition
    Gift of James T. Babb (Yale 1924), 1967.
  - Judaica Fund (Box 6, Folder 75)
  - K-Kd (Box 6, Folder 76)
  - Ke-Keq (Box 6, Folder 77)
  - Ker-Kz (Box 6, Folder 78)
  - L-Ld (Box 7, Folder 79)
  - Le-Lz (Box 7, Folder 80)
  - Lewis, W. S. (Wilmarth Sheldon) (Box 7, Folder 81)
  - Lindsay, John V. (John Vliet) (Box 7, Folder 82)
  - M-Me (Box 7, Folder 83)
  - Mf-Mz (Box 7, Folder 84)
  - Mc (Box 7, Folder 85)
  - Maggs Bros. (Box 7, Folder 86)
  - Motels (Box 7, Folder 87)
  - N-New (Box 7, Folder 88)
  - Ni-Nz (Box 7, Folder 89)
  - New York. State University at Purchase (Box 7, Folder 90)
  - O (Box 7, Folder 91)
  - P-Pe (Box 7, Folder 92)
  - Pf-Pz (Box 7, Folder 93)
  - Pforzheimer Library (Box 7, Folder 94)
  - Q (Box 8, Folder 95)
  - R-Rn (Box 8, Folder 96)
  - Ro-Rof (Box 8, Folder 97)
  - Rog-Rz (Box 8, Folder 98)
  - Radcliffe College (Box 8, Folder 99)
  - S-Sh (Box 8, Folder 100)
  - Si-Ss (Box 8, Folder 101)
  - St (Box 8, Folder 102)
  - Su-Sz (Box 8, Folder 103)
  - Saint Mary-of-the-Woods College (Box 8, Folder 104)
  - Scranton, Charles W., and Company (Box 8, Folder 105)
  - Seven Gables Bookshop (Box 8, Folder 106)
  - Speech. James T. Babb (Box 8, Folder 107)
  - T-Te (Box 8, Folder 108)
  - Tf-Tz (Box 8, Folder 109)
  - Tulsa City-County Library Commission (Box 8, Folder 110)
  - U (Box 9, Folder 111)
  - United States Information Agency, 4 (Box 9, Folder 112-112c)
  - V (Box 9, Folder 113)
  - Van Devanter, Willis (Box 9, Folder 114)
  - W-Wh (Box 10, Folder 115)
  - Wi-Wz (Box 10, Folder 116)
  - White, Milton (Box 10, Folder 117)
  - X-Y (Box 10, Folder 118)
  - Yale University, 5 (Box 10, Folder 119-119d)
  - Yale University. Art Gallery (Box 10, Folder 120)
  - Yale University Press (Box 10, Folder 121)
  - Z (Box 10, Folder 122)
- Other Correspondence, 1964-1968, undated; 0.21; (1 box)
  - "Acknowledged letters", 1965 February (Box 11, Folder 123)
  - Cambridge University Library, 1964 (Box 11, Folder 124)
  - Letters dictated during trip to London, England, 1964 October-December; 2 (Box 11, Folder 125-125a)
  - Letters dictated during trip to England. Dictation machine audio disks, 1964 (Box 12)
  - "Mr. Babb's speech", 1968 January 22 (Box 11, Folder 126)
  - "To be done", undated (Box 11, Folder 127)
  - Unsorted, 1968, undated (Box 11, Folder 128)